[Music]
I've known Jules for quite a quite a
long time and Jules shares a real
passion for the same kind of topics that
that I do and also that rebel wisdom has
covered a lot sort of the nexus between
transformation spirituality ecstasy and
also the history of ideas and an in
particular sort of that sort of nexus of
kind of religion philosophy spirituality
so I'm really pleased that Jules is here
and Jules has been spending a lot of
time recently has just brought out a
book about spiritual emergencies which
is another topic that I'm absolutely
fascinated with I have a little bit of
personal experience with as well and
Jules I'd love if you if you'd like to
kind of take it away and explain your
interest in this topic and where you've
got with it at the time of making the
book and mm-hmm thanks David it's great
to be here
I like your background as well people go
through like the bookshelf background
but you've got CDs in the background or
it is books they're not mine but far
back okay so I'm what I'm going to do is
I'm going to talk for about 30 minutes
just about some research that we've been
doing recently which came out in a new
book we just brought out called breaking
open and then I'm gonna put you all into
break out rooms to discuss in hope you
one-on-ones breakout rooms some of the
ideas that we've raised and then we'll
come back for Q&A so I am going to share
the screen just to get my slides let's
see if this works here we go okay right
so I wrote this book which came out in
2017 called the art of losing control
and it was looking at the topic of
ecstatic experiences the first book I'd
written was about ancient Greek
philosophy and stoicism and how we can
use that today and this book was looking
at the other side of really human
experience non-rational
ecstatic experiences psychology and
psychiatry doesn't talk that much about
this type of experience and when it does
often uses different terminology for it
so sometimes psychologists and
psychiatrists call this mystical
experiences or self-transcendent Abraham
Maslow called them peak experiences or
my fate of mixed experiences sometimes
psychologists use the phrase altered
state of consciousness anthropologists
prefer like to talk about trance States
flow state which is a kind of a scrubbed
up secular well-behaved version of
ecstasy that's popular in kind of
coaching and then a bonus would also
talk about spirit possession and then
psychiatrist when they're pathologizing
this type of experience would talk about
this being really psychosis or
schizophrenia or perhaps bipolar
disorder so I like the expression
ecstatic experience which comes from the
ancient Greek ex fascist which literally
means standing outside yourself your
ordinary self so an ecstatic experience
the moment where you go beyond your
ordinary sense of self and reality and
feel deeply connected to a power or
intelligence or something greater than
you that can be you for ik or it can be
terrifying so it's not true that ecstasy
means being very very happy and
experience can be very scary it can be
you could have it alone or you can have
a collective ecstatic experience and you
can interpret what you connect with in
many different ways you could interpret
it as a connection to God or to a God or
to universal consciousness or to a
spirit or demon or to nature that's what
Romantic poets talk about like the
sublime or perhaps to another person an
ecstatic connection in love or to a
group of people like at a rally or
festival or to your own higher self in
other words it's not necessarily
theistic or supernatural people
interpret this experience in different
ways
so most cultures most times in history
have had ecstatic rituals for healing
for meaning for connection and for fun
as ways to go get out of our heads
it was Aldous Huxley who said humans
have a basic urge to sell the
transcendent nature has to find a way to
give people access out of their heads
give them avenues towards ecstatic
experiences but what's happened in the
West if you look at the history of
ecstatic experience is there's been a
centuries-long ideological war over the
nature of mystical and ecstatic
experiences where since at least the
17th century in the Scientific
Revolution and the Enlightenment
materialist philosophers and
psychologists and psychiatrists have
defined ecstasy as a mental illness so
this lady was a patient at a French
asylum called Salpetriere clinic in
Paris in the late 19th century she was a
patient of the pioneering neurologist
jean-martin charcot and Charcot along
with many other kind of psychiatrist in
19th century said ecstasy is a form of
brain disorder he said it was just a
symptom of a brain disorder called
hysteria and this was and basically if
you have the spiritual ecstatic
experience this is proof that your
degenerate a kind of evolutionary
throwback that you're unfit for society
and you should be medicated and locks up
so if you have a spiritual experience
you should keep quiet about it and not
tell other people this was part of an
ideological struggle between materialist
psychiatry and the church by the way
over who gets to take care of the human
soul but on the other side at the
margins of Western culture
you had ecstatic Christian groups like
say Pentecostal lists and you had New
Age culture saying that ecstasy was not
primitive and aggressive and
pathological but actually the soup
experience of human existence the best
thing that could possibly happen to you
and if you have an ecstatic experience
that's proof that you are elect chosen
by God superior to the rest of humanity
in your maturity and realization that
you are at the vanguard of spiritual
evolution so you can see there's quite a
dichotomy going on either an ecstatic
experience is wholly bad and
pathological or an ecstatic experience
is totally good and wonderful and light
and joyous is there any room for a
middle ground in how we see ecstatic
experiences can we see them as both
sometimes wonderful and healing and
leading flourishing but also sometimes
messy and scary and and possibly
damaging some psychologists and thinkers
did try to find this middle ground for
example William James in his what still
the best book on this topic to my mind
the varieties of religious experience in
1982 and his friend and colleague
Frederik Meijer who less well known but
he was the co-founder of the Society for
psychical research at the end of the
19th century and Myers and James
developed a theory of the self and of
ecstatic experiences they were in a way
the fathers of transpersonal psychology
which is kind of a niche field of
psychology which tries to find a
positive place for mystical or ecstatic
experiences like most psychologies which
just ignore this type of experience or
pathologizing they came up with a model
of the psyche Myers was the wrote the
first paper about the subliminal self in
I believe somewhere 1892 before Freud
before young and so on he said that the
ordinary everyday ego is just a kind of
construction a fiction and that there's
a much bigger subliminal self which is
just below the threshold that's what
subliminal means below the threshold of
ordinary consciousness and then in this
subliminal self there are hidden
potentialities Maya said the subliminal
self is
the rubbish dump and the treasure train
so Freud for example said you know the
it'd is mainly a rubbish dump it's
mainly full of primitive kind of
impulses Maya says yes there is kind of
you know rubbish there there is detritus
there is a tendency to illogical
thinking and sometimes that's dangerous
but it's also a treasure trove he said
there are hidden potentialities in the
subliminal mind potentiality of of
intelligence of memory of wisdom of
learning of healing what we today call
the placebo response is really a kind of
hidden potentiality of healing in our
subliminal mind he also thought that
possibly things like telepathy could be
accessed when we access the subliminal
mind and in trance states they were very
interested in seances and mediums in the
end of the 19th century and they also
thought that possibly if we access some
kind of divine or spirit world we do it
through the subliminal self when we go
into kind of subliminal or altered
states of consciousness so according to
Myers and James's theory them an
ecstatic experience is what Myers called
an up crush from the subliminal mind a
sudden release of normally subconscious
and repressed energy archetypal material
and this kind of up rush creates a
possibility for a reconfiguration of the
self that's what William James was so
interested in the way people could
experience these kind of rebirth moments
in ecstatic States like psychedelic
trips for example or conversion
experiences you know they haven't they
go into a profound altered state and
they feel themselves able to step out of
their old selves into a new self but I
also mean the release of shadow material
that's a union expression like repressed
trauma that you've buried away from your
ordinary everyday self and ecstatic
experiences also involve the disabling
of your critical thinking fact
which can make you prone to mythical
thinking them us thinking and very
easily suggestible cults like thinking
as well so there are some kind of
dangerous gases as it were they get
released in ecstatic experiences so
Myers and James suggested that the
genius one way to think about geniuses
like John Nash saying is that they have
unusual access to the hidden
potentialities of their subliminal mind
and that gives them unusual powers of
say creativity or thinking or wisdom but
it also can make them more prone to
unusual illogical disordered or
pathological thinking so really a genius
is someone who is access to the
subliminal mind and all that power but
also quite a powerful conscious ego and
quite a powerful positive discrimination
so they can sort the good from the bad
as it pours out from their subliminal
mind now since the 1960s there's
obviously been a real value a ssin of
ecstatic experiences an explosion of
ecstatic practices back into Western
culture they've become much less
pathologized and we've got much more
eager to have some you know summaries
experiences we can see data that shows
that so this is a survey from Gallup
which just asked people have you ever
had a religious or mystical experience
in America the number of people who've
said they've had one or more has gone up
from 20% in the start of the 1960's to
around 50% ten years ago in 2009 so more
and more people are having mystical
experiences apparently there's a kind of
mysticism for the masses and I imagine
that figure has just gone up in the last
10 years of the psychedelic Renaissance
where seven years ago over 30 million
people in America said they were regular
psychedelic users so more and more
people are having mystical experiences
but the question I'm interested in as we
as a culture more and more seek these
kinds of experiences is do we have the
cultural tools to help people have these
very you know unusual and sometimes
risky experiences what if people aren't
prepared to go beyond their habitual ego
and don't know how to come back to
consensual reality you think about you
know mystical experiences in the past
where often happened her two monks or
nuns in monasteries or nunneries
training devoting their whole life to
trying to go beyond their ego now people
are having these experiences do they go
to a festival one weekend they pop LSD
suddenly they're having a full-blown
self-transcendent experience which they
weren't expecting they don't really have
the training for and then on Monday
morning they have to go back to their
job as an accountant or whatever so
there's obviously quite challenging
we've been sold the idea that spiritual
experiences are always totally wonderful
purely happy light angels and so on
because you know we've been pushing back
against the pathologize ation of so New
Age culture says spiritual experiences
are always wonderful they're always
great you should seek them they're
amazing when in fact this is more what
they're like down below they at least
they can be quite disturbing and
sometimes quite scary Joseph Campbell
said the psychotic drowns in the same
waters in which the mystic swims with
delight so we're going into this kind of
you know temporary psychotic stage
sometimes when we are going into altered
states of consciousness and some
psychologists over the years have tried
to look at these kinds of more messy or
scary types of mystical experiences
which are difficult to integrate like
Roberto asaji Lee he was the founder of
psycho synthesis I'm sure maybe now he
wrote in a paper in 1937 the incidents
of disturbances having a spiritual
origin is rapidly increasing nowadays
is in step with the growing number of
people who consciously or unconsciously
are groping their way to a fuller life
quite recently in 1989 at 1989 Christina
Groff and her husband stanislav grof
to transpersonal psychologist brought
out this anthology of essays and they
coined the phrase spiritual emergency
it's a brilliant anthology of essays by
the way on this topic and they wrote
they try to define the spiritual
emergency as something a bit different
to ordinary is that many individuals
experiencing episodes of non-aligned
restates of consciousness accompanied by
various emotional perceptual and
psychosomatic manifestations are
undergoing an evolutionary crisis rather
than suffering from a mental disease so
they try to draw this distinction
between mental illness and these kind of
spiritual emergencies which i think is
possibly problematic but let's let we'll
come back to that they said if properly
understood and treated as difficult
stages in their natural developmental
process these experiences these
spiritual emergencies or transpersonal
crises can result in emotional and
psychosomatic healing creative
problem-solving personality
transformation and conscious evolution
so what they're saying is we shouldn't
treat these kinds of messy spiritual
emergencies which can involve extended
alterations in your sense of self and
reality for a you know fair amount of
time we shouldn't treat them as purely
brain disorders as just as breakdowns
that if they're properly navigated they
can be transitioned to greater wholeness
and greater maturity and I think that's
true and I think that might be true of
many types of psychotic experience so my
own spiritual emergency I became
interested particularly in this topic I
wrote about it a little in the art of
losing control
then afterwards after I published that
book I decided to go and try
psychedelics for myself for the first
time in 20 years after I'd had a bad
I was 18 I've left them well clear but
in doing all this research on
psychedelic therapy I was I thought it
was maybe time to go to kind of try them
again but in a proper guided context so
I and I was also interested in spiritual
tourism the way Westerners if they're
seeking that experiences sometimes feel
like they have to go abroad to other
cultures in search of kind of spiritual
or ecstatic experience so I ended up
going to the Amazon to an indigenous
Shipibo Indian ayahuasca retreat to
drink ayahuasca and the actual retreat
was was kind of fascinating and and and
very interesting and positive what
happened then is in the days afterwards
I went to the I went on to the Galapagos
Islands and when I was there this was I
suppose to days after the retreat I went
into quite the dissociated space where I
started to think I'm not in ordinary
reality my kind of ability to think
critically was quite disabled so rather
than thinking you're not in an alternate
reality you're just still hi after an
ayahuasca retreat I've came to the
conclusion I was on my own of course I
think I'm in a kind of dream or possibly
I'm in some kind of Bardo or afterlife
state and that somehow this is all of my
kind of constructing so it was really
kind of I wasn't freaking out but I did
I didn't really trust the reality of the
reality I was in that last few days and
then a friend said you know I think you
better come home notes that you sound
pretty dissociated so then I had to come
all the way back to London I had to take
three flights back from London back from
the Galapagos all the time thinking I
was in a dream because I was in a dream
I thought well I might as well upgrade
to first class on the plane because you
know money's this is all a figment of my
imagination so I did it savvy it turned
out not to be a dream as well I got my
bill credit card bill a few more a few
weeks later but I remember landing
finally in London and
and meeting me at the airport and it
reminded me of like that scene in
Inception where he comes out into the
airport and sees his family and he
doesn't know if it's a dream or a react
or reality but he decides to go with it
it was like that I wasn't still wasn't
sure if my friend was real not I decided
to go with it
so my friend and other friends luckily
they were familiar with this kinds of
experience so they didn't just rush me
to a psychiatric ward a kind of even
love and care and lots of hugs and after
a few days I I came back to this reality
I came grounded back in this reality and
I was fine so obviously I was quite at
one thing that was quite interesting by
the way during that experience is that I
found my critical thinking ability was
quite disabled I found it difficult to
understand conversations to watch films
to read books it was very difficult to
make sense to me but I borrowed this
book from someone and by Pema Chodron
who's a Buddhist nun this book made
perfect sense to me all the way through
that kind of wisdom really worked for me
so I found that these kinds of basic
wisdom teachings worked even in very
limited states of consciousness which
was interesting to me so after that I
became obviously more interested in
spiritual emergencies I organized an
event where several people talked about
their own spiritual emergencies and out
of that I and some of the speakers
helped to put this book together which
came out last month which is basically
14 people's stories of their spiritual
emergencies and what helped them through
my co-editor was Tim Reid who is a
psychiatrist he's the consultant
psychiatrist at Imperial colleges
psychedelics lab and he he's a kind of
transpersonal psychiatrist he that he's
a psychiatrist who's open to positive
spiritual experiences and we tried to be
agnostic about what spiritual
experiences mean in the sense of what
you connect to whether it's to God or
the spirit world and so on we were
agnostic about that
we let our contributors make up their
own minds about that but we ask them
what caused this experience what was it
like and what helps so it was very much
a pragmatic viewpoint what helps you
through so what caused it well of course
we can't we talk about genetic factors
we didn't have the data for that but
there could be some genetic factors for
example a predisposition to dissociation
or schizotypal schizo type is basically
a theoretical concept which suggests
there's a continuum of personality
experiences of being prone to unusual
experiences ranging from normal
dissociative imaginative states like
being a cabin capacity for flow for
example or for creative trance states
all the way to extreme states of mind
related to psychosis and basically
that's continuing though of those kinds
of states of mind through the general
population we did see in several of our
contributors that they'd had childhood
trauma and trauma on their teenage time
so perhaps former makes people more
prone to having messy spiritual
experiences when for example they take
psychedelics or go to spiritual retreats
because they have perhaps kind of buried
trauma and they go beyond their ordinary
self and some of this shadow stuff or
this buried trauma comes out and makes
them more likely to have a difficult
experience which doesn't mean it's a bad
experience because sometimes that could
be the trauma demanding the person's
attention demanding this is an
opportunity for integration in terms of
the short term trigger for the crises
what we saw in our in our police studies
or in these stories of some people it
was psychedelic drugs for some people
the emergency was triggered by intense
spiritual exercises for example going on
a retreat
some people it was triggered by grief
the loss of a significant other or a
very bad breakup
we noticed that for me and for others
they often happen when people are abroad
and away from their usual support
network and that made them more prone to
getting into difficulty of course you
know through our friends and loved ones
that we kind of stay grounded and stay
in touch with with each other and can
reallocate check and then in one story
in the book their spiritual crisis was
triggered by a political crisis by
brexit so they had a kind of brexit
triggered psychosis which is interesting
in terms of this crisis of the pandemic
I suspect that the pandemic is also
probably triggering certain individual
spiritual crises as well and the most
might also cause be a supernatural cause
it's possible that something you know
God or something in the spirit world was
seeking out these people at least that's
how some of our contributors made sense
of these experiences that this wasn't
just a personal experience in their head
it was also an encounter with a greater
reality we as the editors remained
agnostic about what what is the
experience like well what happens is
there's a buildup of kind of tension
within this contact whether that's on a
trip or on a retreat and then suddenly
have flip into another state of
consciousness and the person stays in
that altered state of consciousness time
slows down the person's attention is
deeply absorbed in the moment things
take on a heightened numinous
significance there's an overlap of the
inner and outer world it's like the
dream camera and the only ordinary
camera become overlapped superimposed on
each other so dream archetypal and
mythical material spills out into
everyday life you're dreaming with your
eyes open and people notice
synchronicities signs patterns hidden
meanings uncanny coincidences and the
person may see them
as some kind of cosmic archetype so some
of our contributors saw themselves as
Jesus or evil Ishtar
so there's this kind of you know these
archetypes always there in our dreams
but a person can become possessed by
these archetypes by which I mean they
completely lose any distance they
completely identify with this archetype
so one of our contributors john abel it
decided he is enlightened and he became
a spiritual teacher when he was 21 he
was he became got the nickname the
barefoot guru and people followed him
for for days and weeks
even his university lecturers started to
kind of pay him all this great respect
so he kind of was on his way to becoming
a guru and then he suddenly kind of came
down a bit came off that high and
thought I'm not enlightened and I think
I'm just playing a role now and he had
the kind of courage to leave that guru
role and go back to his family and go
back to his kind of you know young adult
life which took a lot of guts I wonder
how many gurus have that kind of come
down from that high but gets stuck in
the role and they get into all kinds of
problems there's often a feeling of
unreality of ego dissolution a feeling
that you might have died or you're in
some kind of Apocalypse or end times a
feeling of ontological uncertainty this
is definitely what I was like for me is
this real is this a dream am i
constructing this am i God in that case
or am i dead it was a bit like The
Truman Show in that respect which i
think is quite common for kind of
psychotic experiences and I was
interested after my experience to see
that this is quite common to have that
feeling well I had that you're you're
either in a dream or dead
so John where Perry who was a pioneering
psychologist in the 70s who ran a
retreat center for people with
recovering from spiritual emergencies he
said whenever a profound experience of
change is about to take place the
Harbinger is the motif of death in
severe visionary States Ron field while
has crossed into the realm of the dead
and is living among the spirits of the
deceased that's exactly what it was like
for me when I was on a ferry going once
the Galapagos Islands I thought this
must be stick
this must be cheran ferrying me across
the dead this is one of our contributors
Deborah Martin
she took MDMA at a club in Glasgow she
said the morning after the club I woke
to a world that looked entirely
different everything in the room that
clothes the walls the chest of drawers
seemed strangely insubstantial as if
woven from air other nurse the otherness
of objects the other nosov people was
just an illusion so she'd gone into a
kind of Buddhist state of the
interconnectedness of all things but she
didn't want to it was terrifying I
wanted those illusions back I was
tortured by the field and this
perceptual shift was going to result in
the entire world disappearing before my
eyes so this is an involuntary mystical
experience but she wasn't prepared for a
train for it didn't have the support to
cope with and in a way the insight has
some truth in it reality is a controlled
hallucination if you watched an old sets
TED talk he's a neuroscientist he says
reality is a controlled hallucination a
set of habitual expectations based
around a fictional hero ie the ordinary
self but it's not just your
hallucination that's when you can get
into trouble thinking this is all just
my imagining rather than the collective
hallucination there can also be a
powerful sense of interconnectedness to
the universe which can be you for ik and
ego inflating I am God I am controlling
everything or it can be terrifying and
paranoid they can read my mind they're
out to get me
the raw self stripped of its usual armor
feels acutely sensitive isolated and
alienated from others there can be
strained relationships breakups and
bruising bruising encounters with
experts either health experts
psychiatrists or religious experts you
offer glib and reductionist explanations
so what helped our contributors three
we'd looked at kind of set setting and
integration which is a kind of an idea
that's come from psychedelic therapy of
course setting a sympathetic calm
non-judgmental setting helps the mind
settle the mind and body slow down and
stabilize so in my case for example just
having friends who are non-judgmental
who
freaked out and who could just give me
support and love human connection love
and touch hugs helps bring the mind back
from its flight to transcendence maps
and guides can also help us find our way
back
books friends therapists support groups
like the spiritual crisis network or
emerging proud I'll tell you more about
support groups at the end and sometimes
drugs can help take the edge off as well
tranquilizers may help when we're in
acute anxiety but of course psychiatric
wards are not always the best setting if
you're trying to slow your mind down
when it's they don't really heightened a
kind of mystical sting can be easy to
flip into and a kind of paranoid state
and what about the mindset well all our
contributors managed to find a positive
frame of meaning and growth for these
difficult experiences rather than just a
pathological frame of breakdown and
disease so the frame on which they
manage to take their experience was
really important it reminds me of the
stoic quote from Epictetus what disturbs
people is not events but their opinion
about events it's not so much these
weird experiences it's the frame you
have of them that decides whether it's
healthy or not a lot of our contributors
said that mindfulness practices to
connect to their body their breath and
their senses really helped them again
because they had gone into dissociated
states where they'd left ordinary
material reality so it's really helpful
to kind of ground back with their body
in their breath and in this material
reality an attitude of acceptance helped
reminding ourselves this world pass was
very helpful for me and having
compassion for yourself even when you're
you know in a completely altered reality
an attitude of humility helped some of
our contributors avoiding what Ram Dass
called the track of specialness if you
have an ecstatic experience and you
think I'm special I am unique this
happened to me I am one of the elect
that can easily lead to ego inflation
and grandiosity
and that can easily flip into
persecution if I am the Messiah then
maybe there are others out to get me
so humility staying grounded just
because you have a fragment of the law
so God within you doesn't mean that you
alone are God so we can you know trying
to identify with these cosmic archetypes
without becoming possessed by them what
Alan Watts called no-fuss spirituality
and finally discernment am i perhaps
taking a dream metaphor / literally this
for example a band took ayahuasca and
got a message that he should construct a
wooden pyramid to communicate with
aliens it's possible he was taking some
kind of mythical message from his
subconscious / literally /
fundamentalist interpretation of it and
that can happen quite a lot so
integration well I'm I could say a lot
more about it but I want to put you into
breakout rooms but briefly many of our
contributors had a first crisis for
which they were unprepared which was
traumatic then after a period of
training they had a second crisis which
they're able to handle which reminds me
a bit of Luke Skywalker how he got his
his kind of butt kicked by Darth Vader
in impostor X back but then he has a
period of training and is able to face
his shadow with mindfulness compassion
and non reactivity and the second crisis
helps our participants to feel more
comfortable in both worlds the mundane
and the spiritual many of them now
identify with the archetype of the
wounded healer able to draw on their
experience to help others so unresolved
questions which I'd like you to consider
if spiritual emergency in the right
phrase or if it does that confine it
just to kind of New Age culture can one
as the Groff said draw a clean line
between spiritual emergency and ordinary
psychosis can you say oh these people
are having this kind of good experience
which is called spiritual emergency
which has nothing to do with our
ordinary psychosis or do all psychotic
experiences have some aspects of the
spiritual to them and all spiritual
experiences have some aspect of the you
know unusual or that all the psychotic I
think the same tools that work with
spiritual emergency work with ordinary
psychosis as well
and can we be comfortable with the
ambiguity that sometimes it's not clear
whether this this kind of you know
experience you're having is an
evolutionary growth thing or it's just
messy and a breakdown we don't really
know we just got to kind of work through
it the map is not always clear our
contributors we put out these adverts
think please please send us in your own
contributions all our contributors were
white and middle-class well what does
that mean how do other cultures define
this sort of experience is this culture
bound you know a lot of this is about
having the power to define your own
experience and say this isn't a
breakdown this is possibly something
positive and meaningful well who has the
power to say that and why are some
people denied that power to find meaning
in their experience and define something
positive then you're looking at economic
issues and issues of racial inequality
and so on in terms of who gets to define
their experience how do we get this
information out there I'll talk at the
end about some of the groups that are
working in the space and really getting
information out there finally why now
how is it connected to macro factors we
could in a present in Sapa like a
collective spiritual emergency we're in
a meltdown of the habitual in the up
rush of the repressed creating both pain
and also the possibility for
reconfiguration a moment of intense
species connection can we accept
ambiguity that it's not clear what will
emerge but we can try and stay grounded
and contribute positively and mindfully
while accepting our difficult emotions
in the limit of our control
accepting ambiguity that a difficult
situation can be both painful and
beautiful they don't have to be just one
or the other these tools certainly help
tools like mindfulness compassion
equanimity non reactivity remembering it
will pass trying to stay grounded in our
body and trying to practice discernment
as all this mythical material floods out
of our collective subconscious is this
definitely true is this wise and so on
Thank You Jules that's fantastic so nice
to see you
[Music]